<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alex Campbell</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://alexcampbell.co/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://alexcampbell.co/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 19:44:09 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 19:44:09 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failing with Confidence</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-bombed-a-pitch&quot;&gt;I bombed a pitch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks ago was my first time pitching in front of an audience. I was terrified that I would &lt;em&gt;fail&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;
So I did.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
When my team was called, I went up, spouted some bullshit, and finished with the oh so classic line: “&lt;em&gt;That was terrible…&lt;/em&gt;” Goddamn, I’m suave.  At that moment every ounce of confidence that I had built over the years was ripped away from me.  I felt stupid.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yet-the-confidence-surged-back&quot;&gt;Yet the confidence surged back&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I followed up with: “Guys it’s much better when I remember it.”  The chuckles were  weirdly envigorating.  One of the judges said: “So, I have no idea what the hell you’re doing.” I responded with a flawless pitch, it was exactly what I wanted to say.  The words flowed out of me like something that flows, I don’t know, a babbling brook or something. The point is I pitched it.  I pitched it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-i-learned-that-i-should-use-my-fucking-brain&quot;&gt;And I learned that I should use my fucking brain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of regurgitating a script, think. Remember a few key points, and then say what you know.  Unless you’re into mindless babbling. In that case, memorize it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-that-no-matter-how-badly-you-fuck-up-its-probably-salvagable&quot;&gt;And that no matter how badly you fuck up, it’s probably salvagable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could have just sat down and wallowed in my own pity, but I didn’t.  I stood there feeling like an idiot and fixed it.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There will be failure, that’s unavoidable.  It’s what you do in the face of failure that defines who you are.  If you’re not willing to fail, you’ll never learn.  If you fail with confidence, you’ll emerge even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; confident. &amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2014 13:38:21 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexcampbell.co/jekyll/update/2014/07/26/Bombed/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexcampbell.co/jekyll/update/2014/07/26/Bombed/</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
